<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Nimit Mehra</title>
    <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://nimitmehra.com" />
    <updated>2025-10-27T12:35:04+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://nimitmehra.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>About Credentials</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/about-credentials/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/about-credentials/</id>

        <updated>2025-10-27T12:35:04+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I recently met a hostelmate from my undergrad. He had gone to pursue a PhD from IIT Bombay. He mentioned the confidence that undergrads from IIT Bombay carried. According to him, this confidence took them far. Cracking the JEE at eighteen gave them the confidence to be the best in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I recently met a hostelmate from my undergrad. He had gone to pursue a PhD from IIT Bombay. He mentioned the confidence that undergrads from IIT Bombay carried. According to him, this confidence took them far. Cracking the JEE at eighteen gave them the confidence to be the best in the world, which made them push the envelope further. </p>
<p>Having worked with many people from IITs, I had to agree with him, but only partially. There are broadly two kinds of IITians I have seen (or, for that matter, people who have been to a high-credential institution) - those for whom going to that institution was a stepping stone. Those for whom being associated with it was the main highlight of their life. </p>
<p>The first kind are usually ambitious, have a high-class work ethic and the confidence that my friend mentioned. They are usually the people because of whom the institution is famous. It is a learning experience to work with these people. One cannot help but be in awe of them. While most are humble, some can be cocky. However, their cockines is backed by an ability to outthink, outwork and outperform nearly everybody. </p>
<p>The second kind, however, are still living on the high of being associated with a brand name. Most of the time, they haven't done anything of note after being associated with the brand. To them, just cracking the brand was their last achievement. They are the ones who usually name-drop the brand the most. They also have an underlying layer of superiority or inferiority complex, depending on the company. When placed in the group of their peers from the brand, it shows as inferiority. When in the company of others, it shows as a superiority complex. But the underlying emotion is always that of frustration. </p>
<p>The frustration manifests in their constant comparison with their more successful peers. It also makes them consider the work they are doing beneath themselves. The constant comparison and the refusal to do grunt work ( which is most of the work early in the career) sets them up for failure. </p>
<p>The funny thing is that I only saw the second kind in the first five years of my working life. The credentials did open doors for them and gave them a longer runway, but they still had to perform. When the performance was not there, they were usually sidelined or asked to leave. Most of the time, they did not have the support of the team. </p>
<p>There is a third kind, too. Not superstars like the first kind, but not credential-pilled like the second either. They are usually those who have understood and accepted that the field they play in is different from the superstars'. They are more open to learning, work hard, and do well in the field they are in. I see a lot of them around me—hard-working, intelligent chaps who are high on self-belief but also humble to know their limitations. </p>
<p>I may probably update this post in twenty years about how the first and third kinds fared. As of now, the only learning I can share is - two kinds of people go to an institution - those by whose name the institution is known and those who are known by the name of their institution. </p>
<p>Always try to be the first kind!</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/78/indianeagle_a_water_colour_style_painting_shoing_headshot_of__3fbccc6d-ab69-420e-856a-701dfe28a2ce_1.png" alt="A man graduatin from college holding his degree" width="1024" height="1024" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/78/responsive/indianeagle_a_water_colour_style_painting_shoing_headshot_of__3fbccc6d-ab69-420e-856a-701dfe28a2ce_1-xs.png 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/78/responsive/indianeagle_a_water_colour_style_painting_shoing_headshot_of__3fbccc6d-ab69-420e-856a-701dfe28a2ce_1-sm.png 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/78/responsive/indianeagle_a_water_colour_style_painting_shoing_headshot_of__3fbccc6d-ab69-420e-856a-701dfe28a2ce_1-md.png 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/78/responsive/indianeagle_a_water_colour_style_painting_shoing_headshot_of__3fbccc6d-ab69-420e-856a-701dfe28a2ce_1-lg.png 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/78/responsive/indianeagle_a_water_colour_style_painting_shoing_headshot_of__3fbccc6d-ab69-420e-856a-701dfe28a2ce_1-xl.png 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/78/responsive/indianeagle_a_water_colour_style_painting_shoing_headshot_of__3fbccc6d-ab69-420e-856a-701dfe28a2ce_1-2xl.png 1920w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On Failing While Trying</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-failing-while-trying/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-failing-while-trying/</id>

        <updated>2025-10-16T11:18:39+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I had started preparing for JEE in eleventh grade. I had done pretty well in the tenth standard, exceeding even my own expectations. So when I came in eleventh, I expected myself to do similarly well. I was completely wrong. The thing was that by the end of the tenth&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I had started preparing for JEE in eleventh grade. I had done pretty well in the tenth standard, exceeding even my own expectations. So when I came in eleventh, I expected myself to do similarly well. I was completely wrong. </p>
<p>The thing was that by the end of the tenth standard, I had practised the questions so many times that I knew the answer many times before even reading the full question. Obviously, when the grade changed, I had to start from zero, learn new concepts, make mistakes, learn from them, absorb the concepts and then master them. But my ego and the image of invincibility and false genius I had made up in my mind did not let me make mistakes. It did not let me introspect and hence did not let me grow. I did rectify it a bit next year, but the lesson remained. </p>
<p>I have seen this pattern repeat more times than I can count. Whenever a successful person is given a new domain, there is a high probability that he/she will fail. The failure has more to do with the ego than with anything else. The previous success has built an aura of invincibility around them. The internal dialogue is that they are better than the next person. They are unwilling to learn, exposing their vulnerability and making mistakes. More often than not they go back to what they were doing. </p>
<p>But real growth happens by making mistakes and learning from them. One should be willing to fail miserably in practice and get better, rather than fail on the stage itself. It is a lesson which I took to the heart. While I tend to forget it from time to time ( expertise is its own coccoon) I remember the time I was 16 and get back to being open to make mistakes and learn from them. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/77/indianeagle_a_cartoon_in_pixar_style_of_a_child_falling_of_a__b5ce68d0-238b-48d8-bd04-1f8c43ede52a_3.png" alt="A boy falling from the bike while riding" width="1024" height="1024" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/77/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_in_pixar_style_of_a_child_falling_of_a__b5ce68d0-238b-48d8-bd04-1f8c43ede52a_3-xs.png 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/77/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_in_pixar_style_of_a_child_falling_of_a__b5ce68d0-238b-48d8-bd04-1f8c43ede52a_3-sm.png 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/77/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_in_pixar_style_of_a_child_falling_of_a__b5ce68d0-238b-48d8-bd04-1f8c43ede52a_3-md.png 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/77/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_in_pixar_style_of_a_child_falling_of_a__b5ce68d0-238b-48d8-bd04-1f8c43ede52a_3-lg.png 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/77/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_in_pixar_style_of_a_child_falling_of_a__b5ce68d0-238b-48d8-bd04-1f8c43ede52a_3-xl.png 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/77/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_in_pixar_style_of_a_child_falling_of_a__b5ce68d0-238b-48d8-bd04-1f8c43ede52a_3-2xl.png 1920w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On Repetition</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-repetition/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-repetition/</id>

        <updated>2025-10-10T12:33:26+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    My younger daughter asked me the other day to put the do du dudu song. While I was searching for the song on YouTube, she was trying to sing it and was miming the actions—Daddy shak do du dudu, Mommy shak do dudu. I was amazed that a child who&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>My younger daughter asked me the other day to put the do du dudu song. While I was searching for the song on YouTube, she was trying to sing it and was miming the actions—Daddy shak do du dudu, Mommy shak do dudu. I was amazed that a child who had just turned two and for whom English was not the first language, not only remembered the song but also understood it. </p>
<p>It came as no surprise to me that the song is the most-played video on YouTube. It was a rage even in the 2020s when my older daughter was listening to it and shows no signs of stopping. </p>
<p>The reasons kids (and adults) love it are because of its catchy tune, easy-to-understand lyrics and referencing the main characters in their world. But the reason it is remembered and understood is that it is repeated ad nauseam. Listening to the same lyrics again and again starts making an impression on the minds. First they remember the words and the order in which they come. They associate it with their world, and finally, they absorb it. </p>
<p>Come to think of it, even adults learn the same way. It is rarely that a new topic is absorbed in the first reading. It requires multiple readings to understand and absorb the core themes.</p>
<p>There are friends of mine who have stuck to the same career path and often complain that they are bored with their jobs, doing the same thing over and over. But see them in action at work, and it's like seeing an artist. They know the solution to the problem and have considered its effects on the second, third, and fourth orders. Mastery masquerades as experience, honing its skills via repetition. </p>
<p>In today's age, with shorter attention spans and an overload of information, we rarely revisit the same information or content. This is also seen in the deluge of mediocrity all around. Revisiting the same thing gives an illusion of being stuck.  In the search for the new, we are losing the carefully honed mastery of the past. </p>
<p>The only way we will revisit something is if we genuinely love it. Only if we find enjoyment in it and do it for the pure joy would it be worthwhile not to get bored. So maybe that is the future of work: choose what you enjoy doing so the repetition does not feel like drudgery, master it, and then monetise it.</p>
<p>Maybe my 2-year-old likes sharks and will be a marine biologist or possibly a mime, but right now, though, there is a diaper emergency. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/76/indianeagle_a_cartoon_of_a_sculptor_chiseling_away_an_intrica_1cc5a948-e662-4964-bff2-37eca1e77f82_0.png" alt="A sculptor engrossed in his work of chiseling the statue" width="1024" height="1024" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/76/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_of_a_sculptor_chiseling_away_an_intrica_1cc5a948-e662-4964-bff2-37eca1e77f82_0-xs.png 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/76/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_of_a_sculptor_chiseling_away_an_intrica_1cc5a948-e662-4964-bff2-37eca1e77f82_0-sm.png 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/76/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_of_a_sculptor_chiseling_away_an_intrica_1cc5a948-e662-4964-bff2-37eca1e77f82_0-md.png 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/76/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_of_a_sculptor_chiseling_away_an_intrica_1cc5a948-e662-4964-bff2-37eca1e77f82_0-lg.png 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/76/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_of_a_sculptor_chiseling_away_an_intrica_1cc5a948-e662-4964-bff2-37eca1e77f82_0-xl.png 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/76/responsive/indianeagle_a_cartoon_of_a_sculptor_chiseling_away_an_intrica_1cc5a948-e662-4964-bff2-37eca1e77f82_0-2xl.png 1920w"></figure>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Imposter Syndrome</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/imposter-syndrome/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/imposter-syndrome/</id>

        <updated>2025-09-28T20:26:32+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I was recently covered in the alumni spotlight for my undergrad institution. It is a great honour, and I should be proud that the institute chose to feature me. But I do not feel any pride. Instead, I feel a thousand eyes judging me. Why was I featured when many&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I was recently covered in the alumni spotlight for my undergrad institution. It is a great honour, and I should be proud that the institute chose to feature me. But I do not feel any pride. Instead, I feel a thousand eyes judging me. Why was I featured when many more accomplished than me were not featured? I felt like an imposter. I felt like I was not deserving; I knew it, and they knew it, and they were seething or worse, laughing.</p>
<p>Here is the thing about the imposter syndrome. It lies in our heads. We are constantly worried that others are looking at us and judging us. Hence, we try to hide from these prying eyes. We perform for this non-existent crowd, trying to win their approval. We try to tailor our behaviour to please this crowd. Put restrictions on ourselves and speed breakers so that this crowd does not boo us. We want their approval and respect.</p>
<p>But we are not important enough that people keep on talking about us. Most won’t even think about us for more than 10 seconds. Some may spend 5 minutes to comment amongst themselves and laugh at our expense. The core emotion driving them is jealousy or some internal demon that they have to fight. They then project their insecurities on others to feel good and secure about themselves. It is their coping and defence mechanism. The crowd does not care about you; it never did. It wants to protect itself and its psychology and feel secure. Hence, it tries to say or think things that make it believe that it is right and secure. It wants to win the approval of its imaginary crowd by showing it down.</p>
<p>But then there would be true friends, too, who would be proud and happy to see our success. These friends should be kept around.</p>
<p>The crowd is not there. It is in your head. It isn't easy to put it away. I find it difficult myself. But whenever I see that the crowd is looking at me, I smile wave and keep on doing what is right. The only person whose opinion you should care about is you. The only person who success matters to you is you. Stop performing for the crowd. Perform for yourself.</p>
<p><em>“First they ignore you, then they laugh at you, then they fight you, then you win”</em></p>
<div class="captioned-image-container">
<figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zVGC!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel="nofollow ugc noopener" class="image-link image2 is-viewable-img">
<div class="image2-inset"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zVGC!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zVGC!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zVGC!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!zVGC!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div>
</a></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/48/961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024.webp" alt="A person waiving at the crowd from the pulpit" width="1024" height="1024" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/48/responsive/961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024-xs.webp 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/48/responsive/961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024-sm.webp 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/48/responsive/961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024-md.webp 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/48/responsive/961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024-lg.webp 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/48/responsive/961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024-xl.webp 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/48/responsive/961a10f5-44cd-4f31-bf58-32ccd69fa81d_1024x1024-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On Acknowledgement</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-acknowledgement/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-acknowledgement/</id>

        <updated>2025-09-26T12:59:00+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I was recently watching an interview with Bobby Deol. He has experienced a resurgence in his career over the last few years. What was most striking was the vulnerability and the lack of ego that he showed. He looked like a person who had no delusions about himself, was close&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I was recently watching an interview with Bobby Deol. He has experienced a resurgence in his career over the last few years. What was most striking was the vulnerability and the lack of ego that he showed. He looked like a person who had no delusions about himself, was close to the truth, and did not care about anything other than doing good work.</p>
<p>Bobby Deol was a reasonably successful actor in the 90s. He was never considered a superstar, but his movies did above-average business. He played a lover boy in most of his films. I recall him starring in thrillers or romantic comedies, where it seemed that he played the same character repeatedly. It did not look authentic - he had not found his voice. But throughout the nineties, he was a presence on the silver screen—a son and brother of a superstar who was decent.</p>
<p>Then came the slump. He was without roles, often seen in a cricket league of washed-up actors. There were a few home productions where he was seen referencing his older hits. It looked like he was still living in the past. The glory, the audience, the fame and the money were gone. But he was not ready to accept it.</p>
<p>Hitting a slump after seeing success hits differently. Everybody around you knows that success has left you. But you are the last to acknowledge it. You still consider yourself successful based on the success you had some time ago. However, here is a brutal truth about success: it is a treadmill. You need to keep running to stay at the same place. You need to put in effort to get ahead. Reduce your speed, and you are thrown out. That you ran well at some point - does not matter.</p>
<p>In his interviews now, he acknowledges the slump. He acknowledges the dark days. He acknowledges his sheltered upbringing and how he slowly he moved to the sidelines. He then talks about how he overcame his ego and asked people for work. How he made himself vulnerable and was ok hearing no. How he concentrated on just doing work. He then talks about doing an OTT series, a film as a second league and then finding his groove and voice playing antagonist.</p>
<p>The acknowledgement is a sign of strength. Acceptance is the start of the jounrey which frees you from the trappings of your previous success. This freedom helps you explore things and makes it ok to fail when you try something new. The second most difficult thing is overcoming inertia. The cocoon of falsehoods that we wrap around ourselves to soothe us. Breaking it and starting from zero - willing to fail sets up on the road to success.</p>
<p>Seeing the success of Bobby gives me immense happiness. I wish him the best and hope he gets even bigger success.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/75/79d76859-7c83-43b9-bd85-7b4146c3e640_1024x1024.webp" alt="Bobby Deol as a cyber Punk" width="1024" height="1024" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/75/responsive/79d76859-7c83-43b9-bd85-7b4146c3e640_1024x1024-xs.webp 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/75/responsive/79d76859-7c83-43b9-bd85-7b4146c3e640_1024x1024-sm.webp 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/75/responsive/79d76859-7c83-43b9-bd85-7b4146c3e640_1024x1024-md.webp 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/75/responsive/79d76859-7c83-43b9-bd85-7b4146c3e640_1024x1024-lg.webp 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/75/responsive/79d76859-7c83-43b9-bd85-7b4146c3e640_1024x1024-xl.webp 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/75/responsive/79d76859-7c83-43b9-bd85-7b4146c3e640_1024x1024-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On Connecting with the Past</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-connecting-with-the-past/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-connecting-with-the-past/</id>

        <updated>2025-09-25T12:58:00+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I recently visited my alma mater. I was given a very warm welcome. The students accompanied my family, showing me around, and even had a session of questions and answers with me. I should have been delighted at the homecoming - except I wasn’t. It had nothing to do with&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I recently visited my alma mater. I was given a very warm welcome. The students accompanied my family, showing me around, and even had a session of questions and answers with me. I should have been delighted at the homecoming - except I wasn’t.</p>
<p>It had nothing to do with the institute. They were incredible. I do not like visiting the past. To me, it is a chapter that has been written, and the book is closed. Revisiting it only makes me think about what I could have done better. I am not the sentimental type - I don't reminisce about the good old days.</p>
<p>I have always believed that my future should be better than the past. On one hand, this belief motivates me to work better for the future, but on the other hand, it also easily severes my link with the past - places, people, and to an extent, emotions. Needless to say, I am not the best at keeping in touch.</p>
<p>I think this stems from my past. I have changed seven schools in my life. By the time I was changing my third or fourth school, I had made two decisions. Not to get too attached to people in the new school, and not to rue over the people and things I have left behind. It has been challenging to break that mould.</p>
<p>Which is why I was surprised when I had the same feeling when visiting my college. My closest friends are from the college. The most meaningful friendships I formed were there. I came of age in that institute, and yet, I did not enjoy visiting it. I was always thinking of what I could have done better.</p>
<p>That is not the way to live. Happiness comes from connection, sharing and community. Communities are formed around shared stories, laughter, and jokes, and are forged when facing adversity together. A life is lived by embracing and feeling all the emotions - the highs and the lows, the love, the laughter, the pain, and the sorrow. Remaining inert makes one the spectator, not the player.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/74/160629d7-59b3-4aea-8c23-2831247df496_1344x896.webp" alt="A bearded man showing different emotions" width="1344" height="896" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/74/responsive/160629d7-59b3-4aea-8c23-2831247df496_1344x896-xs.webp 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/74/responsive/160629d7-59b3-4aea-8c23-2831247df496_1344x896-sm.webp 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/74/responsive/160629d7-59b3-4aea-8c23-2831247df496_1344x896-md.webp 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/74/responsive/160629d7-59b3-4aea-8c23-2831247df496_1344x896-lg.webp 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/74/responsive/160629d7-59b3-4aea-8c23-2831247df496_1344x896-xl.webp 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/74/responsive/160629d7-59b3-4aea-8c23-2831247df496_1344x896-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Look at Me</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/look-at-me/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/look-at-me/</id>

        <updated>2025-09-23T20:07:00+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    “ Measure what matters” is an often repeated quote. But to me, the right quote should be “Look at what you want to change.” I lost a lot of weight in 2022. This was due to looking after my diet, measuring my weight and doing the proper exercise. I gained&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>“ Measure what matters” is an often repeated quote. But to me, the right quote should be “Look at what you want to change.”</p>
<p>I lost a lot of weight in 2022. This was due to looking after my diet, measuring my weight and doing the proper exercise. I gained nearly all of it back last year. Again, this was due to a bad diet and not measuring my weight. The difference was I was not willing to accept that I had gained weight. To me, I was still the same lean, muscular guy from 2022. You would ask - how did I not see the change in your body shape? The thing is, I stopped looking at myself. I stopped looking at my stomach. Like an ostrich, I believed if I did not look at the problem, it would go away.</p>
<p>It took a trip to the US and people pressing my belly for me to realise how wrong I was. I started noticing my shape. It was tough at first to realise how hideous I looked. I hated looking at myself. I would turn my eyes away but force myself to look at myself. It took sometime but then I sought to look at the hideousness. The first step was acceptance. I knew I was fat. I knew I did not recognise the boy in the mirror. And I knew that I had to make changes.</p>
<p>The first step is realising that there is a problem. Only when this is realised and accepted can solutions be found. This is one of my core life lessons. Starting anything makes us come face to face with our deficiencies. It makes us confront the reality that we are shit ( at that thing). It is an unpleasant feeling to have. But it is the first step that has to be embraced to know where we stand.</p>
<p>The feeling of inadequacy was felt when I started to prepare for CAT, CFA, learning to drive, and everything I was not good at. At the start, I was hideous, but I did not run away. I did not fear it. I knew it was a demon I had to conquer. I needed to look at it first.</p>
<p>So look at yourself. See the hideousness. Accept the reality and then work hard to change it.</p>
<div class="captioned-image-container">
<figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!A4Rw!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F469943c8-21da-441c-9f9f-b0574b140c4e_1024x1024.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel="nofollow ugc noopener" class="image-link image2 is-viewable-img">
<div class="image2-inset"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!A4Rw!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F469943c8-21da-441c-9f9f-b0574b140c4e_1024x1024.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!A4Rw!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F469943c8-21da-441c-9f9f-b0574b140c4e_1024x1024.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!A4Rw!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F469943c8-21da-441c-9f9f-b0574b140c4e_1024x1024.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!A4Rw!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F469943c8-21da-441c-9f9f-b0574b140c4e_1024x1024.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div>
</a></figure>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On Relating to People</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-relating-to-people/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-relating-to-people/</id>

        <updated>2025-09-16T12:56:00+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    In 2014, I was scheduled to start my sales stint in Mumbai. I was part of the prestigious International Graduate program at the Standard Chartered Bank. The program exclusively recruited from top MBA colleges in the country and rotated them across various functions in the bank, including a training stint&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>In 2014, I was scheduled to start my sales stint in Mumbai. I was part of the prestigious International Graduate program at the Standard Chartered Bank. The program exclusively recruited from top MBA colleges in the country and rotated them across various functions in the bank, including a training stint abroad.</p>
<p>We considered ourselves hotshots. We dreamed of flocking the boardrooms in crisp suits and designer ties. We thought we knew it all, and our superior communication skills would separate us from the pack.</p>
<p>So with this confidence ( or overconfidence), a sharp, freshly pressed suit and a tight elevator pitch, I hit the streets of Mumbai. My job was to help the bank open more current accounts. These are the accounts opened by the companies in banks to carry out their transactions. I was given the SME segment and had to compete with other salesmen. The idea was that after our training, we would be handling a team of salesmen, so we should understand the work and the grind.</p>
<p>I failed miserably. In two weeks, forget an account - I could hardly get a foot in the door. I remember my fellow IG graduate and me sitting at a bench next to a Ganesh Pandal, wondering how we failed so badly. The stint was a reality check.</p>
<p>You see, Mumbai businessmen believe in a few principles - simplicity and profit. It won’t be a surprise to find a millionaire wearing a half-sleeve shirt, a neatly pressed pair of pants, and high-quality Kolhapuri chappals. This person would usually be religious, starting the day by lighting agar battis in his office, performing a small pooja, and then beginning work. He would be civil but not have a lot of time for bullshit. He would like to know: what can you do for him, and what can he do for you? Being civil, he will offer you a sweetened half-cut tea nearly always.</p>
<p>When such a person saw a young twenty-something boy, still wet behind his years, walk into his workplace in a crisp suit, speaking English, telling him how his bank account would change his business and refusing the sweetened tea, his guards went up. The first instinct was not to trust this interloper. The next instinct was to be bemused as to why somebody would wear a full suit in this humidity. The final instinct would be to establish his authority, telling the person that he does not have time - the implied signal being - this is my space and I am the king here and I do not recognise you, I reject you and I banish you.</p>
<p>I noticed that the other successful salespeople would dress like owners, speak a few words in the owner's language, participate in the pooja, and latch onto the offer for tea. They used this time to talk about the business and establish a connection, explaining the product.</p>
<p>So, the next day, a crisp white shirt replaced the suit, and a folder took the place of the bag. I hit the streets again, this time speaking the local language. I would first bow in front of God, then take the sweetened tea with relish, explain who I am and what I am doing and establish a connection. The same owner now saw a boy, probably of his kids’ age, who had the same value system as his family. He took on the role of a benevolent uncle, trying to understand more about me, and gave me more time, even explaining the nuances of the business. Many people opened their Rolodexes to help me, simply because they could relate to me. By the end of my stint, I was doing as well as the best salespeople.</p>
<p>At the core, we are still tribal. We feel safe and only let our guards down when we understand that the other person is part of our tribe. To do well, one needs to relate to the other person and understand their value system. This will only come when one starts with respect, genuineness and curiosity. Only then can a connection be established.</p>
<p>All successful people play long-term games. To play a long-term game, you need a genuine connection!</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/73/d7cf9d8a-5052-4f5e-a5c6-fc3d07be0105_1336x814.webp" alt="A man sitting in front of Ganesh Murti" width="1336" height="814" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/73/responsive/d7cf9d8a-5052-4f5e-a5c6-fc3d07be0105_1336x814-xs.webp 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/73/responsive/d7cf9d8a-5052-4f5e-a5c6-fc3d07be0105_1336x814-sm.webp 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/73/responsive/d7cf9d8a-5052-4f5e-a5c6-fc3d07be0105_1336x814-md.webp 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/73/responsive/d7cf9d8a-5052-4f5e-a5c6-fc3d07be0105_1336x814-lg.webp 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/73/responsive/d7cf9d8a-5052-4f5e-a5c6-fc3d07be0105_1336x814-xl.webp 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/73/responsive/d7cf9d8a-5052-4f5e-a5c6-fc3d07be0105_1336x814-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Importance of Being Rooted</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/importance-of-being-rooted/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/importance-of-being-rooted/</id>

        <updated>2025-09-15T12:55:00+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I recently finished reading Pandeymonium by Piyush Pandey. It was a delightful book, though a bit dated. What I liked specifically in the book were his explanations behind unique jingles - his observations and insights into human behaviour. The thing that stood out to me was how rooted in India’s&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I recently finished reading Pandeymonium by Piyush Pandey. It was a delightful book, though a bit dated. What I liked specifically in the book were his explanations behind unique jingles - his observations and insights into human behaviour. The thing that stood out to me was how rooted in India’s culture, its roads, and the behaviour of an ordinary man they were.</p>
<p>The ads that touch us, move us and those that we remember after many years are the ones that speak to us and with which we can relate. They help us acquaint ourselves with an emotion that we have kept hidden somewhere in the recesses of our hearts. They speak to us in a language we see around us - the cultural norms, traditions and pop culture we have. It stems from key observations, grounded in a love for human emotion.</p>
<p>There is a reason why he is one of the most successful ad film makers because he understands India like no other. India, which shares its food and bares its heart to the stranger in the train. Insights such as a bride is famished at the madap while she has to keep a plastered smile for the guests. These are things which come from originality and not from copying something which has worked somewhere else.</p>
<p>Another person who imbibes this is Aditya Chopra. I had seen a documentary about YRF some years back. The thing that stood out was Mr. Chopra’s love for Hindi films. It is said he used to go and watch every Hindi film every Friday and maintain a notebook about what he liked and what he did not like. He developed a keen understanding of the Indian audience as his peers looked to the West for inspiration, trying to be cool by copying Western trends. This is why he delivered blockbusters, while others tried to copy a Hollywood actor, failed to connect, and ultimately fell short.</p>
<p>True success comes when you pull somebody’s heartstrings. To do that, you need to understand them and know them. This comes by appreciating and immersing yourself in their life, culture, language and customs. Once you do that, you become an original - an icon - about whom people talk for decades to come.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/72/fc7d284a-771a-4e53-bde9-74be6aa00d57_1024x1024.webp" alt="A busy street in Delhi" width="1024" height="1024" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/72/responsive/fc7d284a-771a-4e53-bde9-74be6aa00d57_1024x1024-xs.webp 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/72/responsive/fc7d284a-771a-4e53-bde9-74be6aa00d57_1024x1024-sm.webp 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/72/responsive/fc7d284a-771a-4e53-bde9-74be6aa00d57_1024x1024-md.webp 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/72/responsive/fc7d284a-771a-4e53-bde9-74be6aa00d57_1024x1024-lg.webp 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/72/responsive/fc7d284a-771a-4e53-bde9-74be6aa00d57_1024x1024-xl.webp 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/72/responsive/fc7d284a-771a-4e53-bde9-74be6aa00d57_1024x1024-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On Importance of Wasting Time</title>
        <author>
            <name>Nimit Mehra</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-importance-of-wasting-time/"/>
        <id>https://nimitmehra.com/blog/on-importance-of-wasting-time/</id>

        <updated>2025-09-12T12:53:00+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    “If your days are long and years are short - my friend, you are in the wrong place” - a friend had remarked this to me while we were walking towards our car after finishing the work for the day. Curious, I asked him to explain what he meant. He&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>“If your days are long and years are short - my friend, you are in the wrong place” - a friend had remarked this to me while we were walking towards our car after finishing the work for the day. Curious, I asked him to explain what he meant.</p>
<p>He said, "If we're constantly checking the clock for end time during the day, it means we are not enjoying our work. It also means we are not accomplishing anything or having new experiences. This droll existence becomes a loop. Before we know it, the calendar changes without us having any growth.”</p>
<p>The comment shook me to the core. This was exactly my situation at the job. The first year was great. I learnt a lot and built many products. But now, at the three-year mark, I could not point to any learning after that first year. It was not that I was whiling away the time. I was going through the motions to keep myself busy. Lying to myself that what I am doing is important, filling up time. But I was not moving the needle.</p>
<p>I quit within the next few months and started up on my own.</p>
<p>There are many times when I get stuck in this loop. I keep going through the motions, maintaining the appearance of doing important things. But there is a decreasing marginal utility every time the motion is repeated.</p>
<p>It usually happens when I am not learning anything new. The funny thing is, after school and college, learning does not happen through a defined syllabus. It occurs via curiosity. The thing about being curious is - a lot of times, it feels like wasting time. It entails exploring things that do not have any immediate meaningful impact. It means a lot of experimentation, a lot of failing, and a lot of times being humbled, before one starts getting good at the thing that made us curious in the first place.</p>
<p>But from a young age, I have been conditioned to believe that having fun means wasting time. The real benefit comes from dragging myself through things that do not give me joy, like reading biology. My interests or hobbies are the things I do when I have earned a reward for going through things that don't bring me joy.</p>
<p>But such things do not spark my curiosity. The things that do and on which I eventually get good at - fill me with guilt. While indulging in them, I always find myself thinking about when I should start being more productive. It means I neither enjoy exploring my curiosity nor get to work on things I consider productive.</p>
<p>The way I am trying to change now is by allocating time slots. The same trick we used in school, like time tables. For every activity, I define a time slot. In that time slot, once I'm committed, I don't think about anything else. If I am “wasting time”, well, it has been slotted and hence has been guilt-free. If I am going through the drudgery of reading a legal statement, well, nothing else to do till the end of this slot, so better get on with it.</p>
<p>Alleviating guilt has made me calmer and happier. Who knew - the timetable from school was so important after all.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/71/d7544ca4-6f5e-4cfc-8f05-30fe34b888eb_1024x1024.webp" alt="A boy looking at timetable" width="1024" height="1024" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/71/responsive/d7544ca4-6f5e-4cfc-8f05-30fe34b888eb_1024x1024-xs.webp 640w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/71/responsive/d7544ca4-6f5e-4cfc-8f05-30fe34b888eb_1024x1024-sm.webp 768w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/71/responsive/d7544ca4-6f5e-4cfc-8f05-30fe34b888eb_1024x1024-md.webp 1024w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/71/responsive/d7544ca4-6f5e-4cfc-8f05-30fe34b888eb_1024x1024-lg.webp 1366w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/71/responsive/d7544ca4-6f5e-4cfc-8f05-30fe34b888eb_1024x1024-xl.webp 1600w ,https://nimitmehra.com/media/posts/71/responsive/d7544ca4-6f5e-4cfc-8f05-30fe34b888eb_1024x1024-2xl.webp 1920w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
